Israel just recognized Somaliland and this is an absolute game changer. Let me explain.
But first off, what is Somaliland? It does depend on who you ask. If you were to ask a Somali
nationalist, they would say that this is a northern region of Somalia that's illegitimately
trying to break away. But if you were to ask a Somaliland nationalist, they would say that they
are their own country. Now, in terms of domestic affairs, Somaliland has effectively operated as
its own country since 1991. But on the international sphere, Somaliland until recently
has not been recognized by anyone else as being its own sovereign independent country. But what's
critical about Somaliland for this video is that's near a very important area of water called the
Bab al-Mendib Strait. The Bab al-Mendib Strait is very narrow. It connects the Indian Ocean with the
Red Sea. There's also two other countries I'm going to talk about in this video that are near this
area, Yemen and Djibouti. But what makes the Bab al-Mendib Strait so critical is that anywhere from
10% to one third of all international trade passes through here on its way to the Suez Canal.
Now, this area is so critical that it's actually heavily militarized. So for instance, in the tiny
country of Djibouti, there are 12 foreign military bases that are there, including one from the United
States, and they only exist there in order to protect ships passing through. Now, Israel, though,
has had a dilemma over the last two years. Its ships passing through the Bab al-Mendib Strait have been
under attack from a group called the Houthis. The Houthis are a group that control the most
populated areas of Yemen. And for the last two years, they've been engaging in a blockade against
Israeli ships in order to resist Israel's ongoing genocide of Palestinians in Gaza, which is, of
course, a wonderful and very brave thing to do. Now, the United States, though, oddly enough, has actually not
been able to use its military base in Djibouti to stop the Houthis. The reason for this is because
Djibouti, as a tiny country, doesn't really want to get involved in a full-scale war against Yemen.
And this has angered the United States quite a bit. In fact, it's got the United States so angry that in
the Project 2025 document, the so-called blueprint, that's over 900 pages for Trump's second term, they
actually on the section on Africa single out Djibouti for bad relations and propose instead that the United States
recognized Somaliland. And the implication here is that the United States could then have a military
base there that it could conduct operations to protect its ships as well as to stop the Houthis.
Now, what seems to have happened today, though, is instead of the United States, it's actually Israel
that has taken on the initiative. Going ahead, recognizing Somaliland, and it has nothing to do
with the Somalilanders' self-determination or what's going on in their own country. Israel, of course,
wants to have its own military base there that it can use to attack its enemy, the Houthis.
That's why this is happening and that's why this is critical. I think the United States will follow
suit very soon and probably the United Arab Emirates as well in recognizing Somaliland. Thank you.